<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="target.xsl"?>
<Case-Study>
  <Assessment-Target date="2021-09-14" updated-by="JRFP" status="draft">
    <AT-id>MFT1.2_4_MP_55x</AT-id>
    <AT-short-name>EC Australian Shelf</AT-short-name>
    <AT-descriptions>
      <AT-description lang="en">The 'Mangroves of East Central Australian Shelf' is a regional ecosystem subgroup (level 4 unit of the IUCN Global Ecosystem Typology) that includes intertidal forest and shrublands of the marine ecoregions of Lord Howe and Norfolk Islands (Lord Howe and Norfolk Islands province), Manning-Hawkesbury (East Central Australian Shelf province), Tweed-Moreton (East Central Australian Shelf province). The biota is characterised by 16 species of true mangroves and other key plant taxa that provide structure and resources for other mangove-associated taxa. Mangroves in this subgroup have a mapped extent between 350 and 450 km^2 across 2 countries. They are classified as Estuary with Terrigenous sedimentar They are threatened by  conversion for urban and tourism development, agriculture and aquaculture, and by increases in frequency of tropical storms. </AT-description>
    </AT-descriptions>
    <AT-names>
      <AT-name lang="en">Mangroves of East Central Australian Shelf</AT-name>
      <AT-name lang="es">Bosques de Manglar de East Central Australian Shelf</AT-name>
    </AT-names>
    <Characteristic-biota>
      <Biota-Summaries>
        <Biota-Summary lang="en">The biota of 'Mangroves of East Central Australian Shelf' is characterised by the presence of 16 true mangrove and other key plant species (RLTS 2021). There are at least 54 species of the GASTROPODA, ACTINOPTERYGII, CHONDRICHTHYES, AVES, REPTILIA that have been associated with mangrove habitats in the Red List of Threatened Species database and have natural history collection records or observations within the distribution of this unit (GBIF 2021). The Vulnerable Leopard Whipray is a resident of the mangroves in this region.</Biota-Summary>
      </Biota-Summaries>
      <taxons>
        <taxon>Excoecaria agallocha</taxon>
        <taxon>Acrostichum speciosum</taxon>
        <taxon>Aegiceras corniculatum</taxon>
        <taxon>Bruguiera gymnorhiza</taxon>
        <taxon>Halodule pinifolia</taxon>
        <taxon>Lumnitzera racemosa</taxon>
        <taxon>Zostera muelleri</taxon>
        <taxon>Halodule uninervis</taxon>
        <taxon>Avicennia marina</taxon>
        <taxon>Rhizophora stylosa</taxon>
        <taxon>Osbornia octodonta</taxon>
        <taxon>Cynometra iripa</taxon>
        <taxon>Aegialitis annulata</taxon>
        <taxon>Xylocarpus granatum</taxon>
        <taxon>Halophila ovalis</taxon>
        <taxon>Ceriops australis</taxon>
        <taxon>Ascorhis tasmanica</taxon>
        <taxon>Pleuroloba quoyi</taxon>
        <taxon>Littoraria undulata</taxon>
        <taxon>Ellobium aurisjudae</taxon>
        <taxon>Laemodonta bella</taxon>
        <taxon>Platax orbicularis</taxon>
        <taxon>Conus frigidus</taxon>
        <taxon>Conus varius</taxon>
        <taxon>Arothron manilensis</taxon>
        <taxon>Contusus brevicaudus</taxon>
        <taxon>Arothron reticularis</taxon>
        <taxon>Elops hawaiensis</taxon>
        <taxon>Lutjanus fulviflamma</taxon>
        <taxon>Lutjanus fulvus</taxon>
        <taxon>Himantura leoparda</taxon>
        <taxon>Gymnothorax monochrous</taxon>
        <taxon>Uropterygius concolor</taxon>
        <taxon>Mugilogobius notospilus</taxon>
        <taxon>Parioglossus palustris</taxon>
        <taxon>Parioglossus rainfordi</taxon>
        <taxon>Plectorhinchus gibbosus</taxon>
        <taxon>Leiognathus equulus</taxon>
        <taxon>Lethrinus laticaudis</taxon>
        <taxon>Lethrinus nebulosus</taxon>
        <taxon>Atule mate</taxon>
        <taxon>Ceyx pusillus</taxon>
        <taxon>Todiramphus chloris</taxon>
        <taxon>Anhinga melanogaster</taxon>
        <taxon>Myzomela erythrocephala</taxon>
        <taxon>Gavicalis versicolor</taxon>
        <taxon>Gavicalis fasciogularis</taxon>
        <taxon>Gerygone magnirostris</taxon>
        <taxon>Gerygone levigaster</taxon>
        <taxon>Pachycephala melanura</taxon>
        <taxon>Pachycephala lanioides</taxon>
        <taxon>Melloria quoyi</taxon>
        <taxon>Oriolus flavocinctus</taxon>
        <taxon>Myiagra ruficollis</taxon>
        <taxon>Zosterops luteus</taxon>
        <taxon>Philemon buceroides</taxon>
        <taxon>Ctenotus robustus</taxon>
        <taxon>Plectorhinchus pictus</taxon>
        <taxon>Parachaeturichthys polynema</taxon>
        <taxon>Johnius australis</taxon>
        <taxon>Gerres erythrourus</taxon>
        <taxon>Paratrypauchen microcephalus</taxon>
        <taxon>Siganus lineatus</taxon>
        <taxon>Thryssa kammalensis</taxon>
        <taxon>Glossogobius circumspectus</taxon>
        <taxon>Stolephorus carpentariae</taxon>
        <taxon>Lichmera indistincta</taxon>
        <taxon>Microeca flavigaster</taxon>
        <taxon>Synodus sageneus</taxon>
        <taxon>Diagramma labiosum</taxon>
      </taxons>
    </Characteristic-biota>
    <Abiotic-environment>
      <Abiotic-Summaries>
        <Abiotic-Summary lang="en">Many mangrove soils are low in nutrients, especially nitrogen and phosphorus. Regional distributions are influenced by interactions among landscape position, rainfall, hydrology, sea level, sediment dynamics, subsidence, storm-driven processes, and disturbance by pests and predators. Rainfall and sediment supply from rivers and currents promote mangrove establishment and persistence, while waves and large tidal currents destabilise and erode mangrove substrates, mediating local-scale dynamics in ecosystem distributions. High rainfall reduces salinity stress and increases nutrient loading from adjacent catchments, while tidal flushing also regulates salinity.</Abiotic-Summary>
      </Abiotic-Summaries>
    </Abiotic-environment>
    <Biotic-processes>
      <Processes-Summaries>
        <Processes-Summary lang="en">Mangroves are structural engineers and possess traits including pneumatophores, salt excretion glands, vivipary, and propagule buoyancy that promote survival and recruitment in poorly aerated, saline, mobile, and tidally inundated substrates. They are highly efficient in nitrogen use efficiency and nutrient resorption. They produce large amounts of detritus (e.g. leaves, twigs, and bark), which is either buried in waterlogged sediments, consumed by crabs, or more commonly decomposed by fungi and bacteria, mobilising carbon and nutrients to higher trophic levels. These ecosystems are also major blue carbon sinks, incorporating organic matter into sediments and living biomass. Although highly productive, these ecosystems are less speciose than other coastal biogenic systems. Crabs are among the most abundant and important invertebrates. Their burrows oxygenate sediments, enhance groundwater penetration, and provide habitat for other invertebrates such as molluscs and worms. Specialised roots (pneumatophores) provide a complex habitat structure that protects juvenile fish from predators and serves as hard substrate for the attachment of algae as well as sessile and mobile invertebrates (e.g. oysters, mussels, sponges, and gastropods). Mangrove canopies support invertebrate herbivores and other terrestrial biota including invertebrates, reptiles, small mammals, and extensive bird communities. </Processes-Summary>
      </Processes-Summaries>
    </Biotic-processes>
    <Ecosystem-services>
      <Services>
        <Ecosystem-service/>
      </Services>
      <Services-Summaries>
        <Services-Summary lang="en">These systems are among the most productive coastal environments. These ecosystems are also major blue carbon sinks, incorporating organic matter into sediments and living biomass. They have well-documented ability of  to protect coastal regions from storms. </Services-Summary>
      </Services-Summaries>
    </Ecosystem-services>
    <Threats>
      <Threats-Summaries>
        <Threats-Summary lang="en">Mangrove deforestation due to aquaculture. Urbanisation and the associated coastal development, over-harvesting, and pollution from domestic, industrial and agricultural land use urbanisation (coastal development). The position of mangrove forests in intertidal areas renders them vulnerable to predicted sea-level rise as a result of climate change. Tropical storms can damage mangrove forests through direct defoliation and destruction of trees, as well as through the mass mortality of animal communities within the ecosystems. </Threats-Summary>
      </Threats-Summaries>
      <Threat>
        <Threat-name>Urbanisation</Threat-name>
        <Threat-description lang="en">Urbanisation and the associated coastal development can lead to over-harvesting, and pollution from domestic, industrial and agricultural land use.</Threat-description>
        <Threat-Impact>
          <Threat-Timing id="IUCN" version="3.2" selected="yes" assigned-by="JRFP">Ongoing</Threat-Timing>
          <Threat-Scope id="IUCN" version="3.2" selected="yes" assigned-by="JRFP">Unknown</Threat-Scope>
          <Threat-Severity id="IUCN" version="3.2" selected="yes" assigned-by="JRFP">Unknown</Threat-Severity>
        </Threat-Impact>
        <Threat-classification id="IUCN" version="3.2" selected="yes" assigned-by="Assessment authors">
          <Threat-classification-element level="1">1 Residential and Commercial Development</Threat-classification-element>
          <Threat-classification-element level="1">5 Biological Resource Use</Threat-classification-element>
          <Threat-classification-element level="1">9 Pollution</Threat-classification-element>
          <Threat-classification-element level="2">1.1 Housing &amp; urban areas</Threat-classification-element>
          <Threat-classification-element level="2">5.3 Logging &amp; Wood Harvesting</Threat-classification-element>
          <Threat-classification-element level="2">5.4 Fishing &amp; Harvesting Aquatic Resources</Threat-classification-element>
          <Threat-classification-element level="2">9.1 Domestic &amp; Urban Waste Water</Threat-classification-element>
          <Threat-classification-element level="3">5.3.2 Intentional Use: Large Scale [harvest]</Threat-classification-element>
          <Threat-classification-element level="3">5.4.2 Intentional Use: Large Scale [harvest]</Threat-classification-element>
          <Threat-classification-element level="3">9.1.1 Sewage</Threat-classification-element>
          <Threat-classification-element level="3">9.1.2 Run-off</Threat-classification-element>
        </Threat-classification>
      </Threat>
      <Threat>
        <Threat-name>Aquaculture</Threat-name>
        <Threat-description lang="en">Aquaculture causes damage through deforestation and pollution, due to the release of effluents into the ecosystem</Threat-description>
        <Threat-Impact>
          <Threat-Timing id="IUCN" version="3.2" selected="yes" assigned-by="JRFP">Ongoing</Threat-Timing>
          <Threat-Scope id="IUCN" version="3.2" selected="yes" assigned-by="JRFP">Unknown</Threat-Scope>
          <Threat-Severity id="IUCN" version="3.2" selected="yes" assigned-by="JRFP">Unknown</Threat-Severity>
        </Threat-Impact>
        <Threat-classification id="IUCN" version="3.2" selected="yes" assigned-by="Assessment authors">
          <Threat-classification-element level="1">2 Agriculture &amp; Aquaculture</Threat-classification-element>
          <Threat-classification-element level="2">2.4 Marine &amp; Freshwater Aquaculture</Threat-classification-element>
          <Threat-classification-element level="3">2.4.2 Industrial Aquaculture</Threat-classification-element>
        </Threat-classification>
      </Threat>
      <Threat>
        <Threat-name>Sea level rise</Threat-name>
        <Threat-description lang="en">The position in intertidal areas renders them vulnerable to predicted sea-level rise as a result of climate change</Threat-description>
        <Threat-Impact>
          <Threat-Timing id="IUCN" version="3.2" selected="yes" assigned-by="JRFP">Ongoing</Threat-Timing>
          <Threat-Scope id="IUCN" version="3.2" selected="yes" assigned-by="JRFP">Unknown</Threat-Scope>
          <Threat-Severity id="IUCN" version="3.2" selected="yes" assigned-by="JRFP">Unknown</Threat-Severity>
        </Threat-Impact>
        <Threat-classification id="IUCN" version="3.2" selected="yes" assigned-by="Assessment authors">
          <Threat-classification-element level="1">11 Climate Change &amp; Severe Weather</Threat-classification-element>
          <Threat-classification-element level="2">11.1 Habitat Shifting &amp; Alteration</Threat-classification-element>
          <Threat-classification-element level="2">11.4 Storms &amp; Flooding</Threat-classification-element>
        </Threat-classification>
      </Threat>
    </Threats>
    <Conservation-actions/>
    <Research-needs/>
    <Conceptual-ecosystem-model/>
    <Classifications>
      <Classification-system id="IUCN GET" version="2.0" selected="yes" assigned-by="Assessment authors">
        <Classification-element level="1">Transitional Marine-Freshwater-Terrestrial realm</Classification-element>
        <Classification-element level="2">MFT1 Brackish tidal biome</Classification-element>
        <Classification-element level="3">MFT1.2 Intertidal forests and shrublands</Classification-element>
        <Classification-element level="4">MFT1.2_4_MP_55x Mangroves of East Central Australian Shelf</Classification-element>
      </Classification-system>
      <Classification-system id="IUCN habitat" version="3.1" selected="no" assigned-by="Assessment authors">
        <Classification-element level="1">1 Forest</Classification-element>
        <Classification-element level="2">1.7 Forest – Subtropical/tropical mangrove vegetation above high tide level</Classification-element>
        <Classification-element level="1">12 Marine Intertidal</Classification-element>
        <Classification-element level="2">12.7 Marine Intertidal - Mangrove Submerged Roots</Classification-element>
      </Classification-system>
    </Classifications>
    <Distribution>
      <Distribution-Summaries>
        <Distribution-Summary lang="en">The 'Mangroves of East Central Australian Shelf' includes intertidal forest and shrublands of the marine ecoregions of Lord Howe and Norfolk Islands (Lord Howe and Norfolk Islands province), Manning-Hawkesbury (East Central Australian Shelf province), Tweed-Moreton (East Central Australian Shelf province), that extent across 2 countries and territories in the regions of East Asia &amp; Pacific. Mangrove extent in this region is estimated between 381 and 413 km^2 (Giri et al. 2011; Bunting et al. 2018).</Distribution-Summary>
      </Distribution-Summaries>
      <Countries>
        <Country iso-code-2="AU">Australia</Country>
        <Country iso-code-2="NF">Norfolk Island (Aus.)</Country>
      </Countries>
      <Spatial-data>
        <Spatial-point datum="WGS84" proj="+proj=longlat +datum=WGS84 +no_defs" type="lower-left-corner">
          <x>147.66942067913</x>
          <y>-35.6614126815884</y>
          <radius units="m">1000</radius>
        </Spatial-point>
        <Spatial-point datum="WGS84" proj="+proj=longlat +datum=WGS84 +no_defs" type="lower-left-corner">
          <x>171.331088751946</x>
          <y>-23.9660274803475</y>
          <radius units="m">1000</radius>
        </Spatial-point>
      </Spatial-data>
    </Distribution>
    <Collapse-definition>
      <Collapse-summaries>
        <Collapse-summary lang="en"/>
      </Collapse-summaries>
      <Spatial-collapse-definitions>
        <Spatial-collapse lang="en">Mangroves are structural engineers and possess specialised traits that promote high nitrogen use efficiency and nutrient resorption that influences major processes and functions in this ecosystem. Ecosystem collapse is considered to occur when the tree cover of diagnostic species of true mangroves declines to zero (100% loss).</Spatial-collapse>
      </Spatial-collapse-definitions>
      <Functional-collapse-definitions>
        <Functional-collapse lang="en">These are highly dynamic systems, with species distributions adjusting to local changes in sediment distribution, tidal regimes, and local inundation and salinity gradients. Processes that disrupt this dynamic can lead to ecosystem collapse. Ecosystem collapse may occur under any of the following: a) climatic conditions (low temperatures) restrict recruitment and survival of diagnostic true mangroves; b) changes in rainfall and river inputs and/or waves and tidal currents destabilise and erode substrates and disrupt recruitment and growth, c) changes in rainfall and tidal flushing change salinity stress and nutrient loadings affecting survival.</Functional-collapse>
      </Functional-collapse-definitions>
    </Collapse-definition>
    <References>
      <Reference>Worthington et al. (2020) 2020. A global biophysical typology of mangroves and its relevance for ecosystem structure and deforestation. Sci. Rep. 10, 14652. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-020-71194-5</Reference>
      <Reference>Bishop et al. (2020) </Reference>
      <Reference>RLTS (2021) Habitat association, species distribution range and taxonomic information from the IUCN Red List of Threatened Species database.</Reference>
      <Reference>GBIF (2021) Species distribution records from the Global Biodiversity Information Facility</Reference>
      <Reference>Spalding et al. (2007). Marine Ecoregions of the World: a bioregionalization of coast and shelf areas. BioScience 57: 573-583. doi: 10.1641/B570707. Data URL: http://data.unep-wcmc.org/datasets/38</Reference>
      <Reference>Giri et al. (2011). *Status and distribution of mangrove forests of the world using earth observation satellite data* (version 1.3, updated by UNEP-WCMC). **Global Ecology and Biogeography** 20: 154-159. doi: [10.1111/j.1466-8238.2010.00584.x].</Reference>
      <Reference>Bunting et al. (2018). The Global Mangrove Watch – a New 2010 Global Baseline of Mangrove Extent. Remote Sensing 10(10): 1669. doi: 10.3390/rs1010669.</Reference>
    </References>
  </Assessment-Target>
</Case-Study>
